Granniss and Elmore Records 1985.0005
Archives and Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Library
Granniss and Elmore Records
undated, 1880-1947
Archives and Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Library
1985.0005
57 Linear Feet
Ganung and Elmore, general merchandise and grocery firm of Litchfield, Connecticut, was founded by George S. Elmore (1856-1904) and C. M. Ganung in 1880 with stock purchased from a bankrupt company. In 1882, Mr. Ganung sold his interest in the store to Westoen G. Granniss (1855-1940) of Litchfield, Connecticut, and the store was renamed Granniss and Elmore. The firm dealt in general merchandise such as groceries, dry goods, dishes, crockery, carpets, window shades, screens, linoleum, and wallpaper. The firm's motto was "Everything guaranteed as represented."
Access
The collection is open and available for research.
Acquisition Information
In 1979, University of Connecticut Libraries' Special Collections Department transferred the records to the Historical Manuscripts and Archives Division (now Archives & Special Collections).
Arrangement
Series I: General Accounts (1880-1940) consists of ledgers, day books, and waste books, all of which record information concerning daily transactions, as well as accounts payable books, and cash books. The ledgers record transactions by name of purchaser or account holder. The day books contain a daily record of transactions at the store. The waste books, the initial record of transaction, are the least legible, but have been retained to fill gaps in the day books and/or ledgers. The accounts payable records have been entered in bound volumes also entitled 'Ledger'; these books record the financial activity between Granniss and Elmore and the company's suppliers. The cash books maintain a record of bank deposits and withdrawals, as well as a record of the yearly profits/losses of the firm. The volumes in this series are arranged chronologically within each record type.
Series II: Inventories and Miscellaneous Accounts (1881[?] - 1931; 1947) consists of three inventory books, a day book containing information on lumber transactions, and a volume entitled, "Cash Book and Accounts," dated 1947. The inventory books provide a periodic listing of goods available for purchase, as well as an indication of the strength or weakness of sales in general. The day book is a daily record of lumber sales. The 1947 volume appears to contain financial information about the rental of the second floor apartments above the store. This series is arranged chronologically within each record type.
Series III: Invoice Books (1888-1940) is a representative sample consisting of seven invoice books. Invoices from the firm's various suppliers are pasted into the books in rough chronological order. Each book has an index on the front page. This series is arranged chronologically.
History
Ganung and Elmore, general merchandise and grocery firm of Litchfield, Connecticut, was founded by George S. Elmore (1856-1904) and Charles M. Ganung in 1880 with stock purchased from a bankrupt company. In 1882, Mr. Ganung sold his interest in the store to Weston G. Granniss (1855-1940) of Litchfield, Connecticut, and the store was renamed Granniss and Elmore. The firm dealt in general merchandise such as groceries, dry goods, dishes, crockery, carpets, window shades, screens, linoleum, and wallpaper. The firm's motto was "Everything guaranteed as represented."
In 1888, Granniss and Elmore's wooden structures were destroyed in a fire that ravaged most of the Litchfield business section. The two partners, determined to prevent such a disaster from reoccurring, constructed a new two story brick building. For its time, it was considered the most modern store in Litchfield. In addition to the standard fixtures found in a general store, such as a potbellied stove and cracker barrels, the new building was heated by a furnace, had large plate glass display windows, varnished woodwork, a fleet of delivery wagons, and both telephone and telegraph service. In 1897, the partners pioneered the use of electricity in Litchfield County by installing an electrical dynamo in the basement which provided power to light forty electric lights in the store. The years from 1882 to 1918 were the store's most profitable, as sales climbed from $33,000 to $64,000.
By 1907, the store was renamed the W. G. Granniss Company. After George S. Elmore died in 1904, W. G. Granniss took on two new partners,Frank Perkins and William Butler. Both were paid a salary plus a share of the profits. In 1919, due to increased competition from grocery chain stores and a resulting decline in profits, Granniss sold his interest in the grocery business to a partnership composed of Jules Chapin and Ernest Birk. Mr. Granniss held onto the dry goods store, but increasingly devoted himself to local politics and other business interests in the area. In 1925, Chapin sold out his interest to Birk, and the store was renamed Birk and Company.
During the 1920s, the store fared badly from competition in Litchfield as well as nearby Torrington, which was easily accessible by car. The store's fortunes sank even more rapidly during the depression years. From 1919 to 1940, the grocery store's yearly sales plummeted from $24,000 to $4,900. When Mr. Granniss died in 1940, Ernest Birk bought out the interests in the dry goods store and purchased the building as well. Shortly after World War II, the business was converted into a self-service food store known as Superior Foods>.
Custodial History
The records of Granniss and Elmore were donated to the University of Connecticut School of Business Administration in 1948 by Ernest W. Birk of Litchfield. Known as the Birk Collection, the records were transferred to the Wilbur Cross Library at UConn in 1950.
Scope and Content
Granniss and Elmore records, 1880-1947 [1880-1930], document some of the business activities of the general merchandise and grocery firm of Litchfield, Connecticut>. The records include ledgers, day books, cash books, accounts payable, invoices, and inventories.
General stores; Litchfield (inhabited place); Merchants; Financial Records; Inventories; Connecticut (state)
- Series I: General Accounts, 1880-1940
  Scope and Contents note
  The volumes are listed with their original numbers rather than being numbered sequentially. However, beginning with `Waste Books, dry goods,' the volumes possess no original numbers and therefore are numbered sequentially starting at 601.
  - Ledgers
    - 1880-1883 (Volume 1)
    - 1883-1886 (Volume 2)
  - Ledgers with boxed indexes (3-9, 10-16)
    - 1886-1889 (Volume 3)
    - 1889-1894 (Volume 4)
    - 1893-1896 (Volume 5)
    - 1896-1899 (Volume 6)
    - 1899-1901 (Volume 7)
    - 1901-1903 (Volume 8)
    - 1903-1905 (Volume 9)
    - 1905-1907 (Volume 10)
    - 1907-1909 (Volume 11)
    - 1909-1911 (Volume 12)
    - 1911-1914 (Volume 13)
    - 1913-1915 (Volume 14)
    - 1915-1916 (Volume 15)
    - 1918-1927 (Volume 16)
    - 1927-1938 (Volume 42)
    - 1938-1940 (Volume 43)
  - Day Books
    - 1880 November - 1881 May (Volume 1)
    - 1881 September - 1882 February (Volume 3)
    - 1882 August - 1883 May (Volume 5)
    - 1883 November - 1884 May (Volume 7)
    - 1884 October - 1885 May (Volume 9)
    - 1885 September - 1886 March (Volume 11)
    - 1886 August - 1887 February (Volume 13)
    - 1887 August - 1888 February (Volume 15)
    - 1888 July - December (Volume 17)
    - 1889 July - December (Volume 19)
    - 1890 July - 1891 January (Volume 21)
    - 1891 October - 1892 June (Volume 23)
    - 1892 October - 1893 May (Volume 25)
    - 1893 November - 1894 June (Volume 27)
    - 1894 November - 1895 June (Volume 29)
    - 1895 October - 1896 April (Volume 31)
    - 1896 August - 1897 January (Volume 33)
    - 1897 July - October (Volume 35)
    - 1898 April - August (Volume 37)
    - 1898 December - 1899 June (Volume 39)
    - 1899 August - December (Volume 41)
    - 1900 June - September (Volume 43)
    - 1901 January - June (Volume 45)
    - 1901 September - 1902 January (Volume 47)
    - 1902 June - August (Volume 49)
    - 1902 December - 1903 June (Volume 51)
    - 1903 September - 1904 January (Volume 53)
    - 1904 June - September (Volume 55)
    - 1905 January - June (Volume 57)
    - 1905 September - December (Volume 59)
    - 1906 May - August (Volume 61)
    - 1906 October - 1907 March (Volume 63)
    - 1907 June - August (Volume 65)
    - 1907 November - 1908 April (Volume 67)
    - 1908 July - September (Volume 69)
    - 1908 January - 1909 May (Volume 71)
    - 1909 July - October (Volume 73)
    - 1910 January - May (Volume 75)
    - 1911 July - October (Volume 77)
    - 1911 January - May (Volume 79)
    - 1912 August - October (Volume 81)
    - 1912 February - May (Volume 83)
    - 1912 August - October (Volume 85)
    - 1913 March - June (Volume 87)
    - 1913 September - 1914 January (Volume 89)
    - 1915 May - August (Volume 91)
    - 1914 October - 1915 February (Volume 93)
    - 1915 June - August (Volume 95)
    - 1915 November - 1916 March (Volume 97)
    - 1916 June - August (Volume 99)
    - 1916 October - November (Volume 101A)
    - 1918 May - July (Volume 101B)
    - 1918 October - 1919 February (Volume 103)
    - 1921 July - 1923 June (Volume 105)
    - 1925 February - 1927 April (Volume 107)
    - 1930 March - 1933 May (Volume 109)
    - 1936 September - 1940 March (Volume 111)
  - Waste Books, general
    - 1916 October - 1917 January (Volume 531-2)
    - 1917 January - April (Volume 533-4)
    - 1917 April - June (Volume 535-6)
    - 1917 June - August (Volume 537)
    - 1917 July - August (Volume 538)
    - 1917 September - November (Volume 539-40)
    - 1917 November - 1918 February (Volume 541-2)
    - 1918 February - May (Volume 543-4)
    - 1917 October - 1918 February; 1918 February - May; 1918 February - June (Volume 545 a,b,c)
  - Waste Books, dry goods
    - 1916 October - 1919 January (Volume 601)
    - 1919 February - 1920 May (Volume 602)
    - 1920 May - 1921 June (Volume 603)
    - 1921 June - 1922 June (Volume 604)
  - Accounts Payable
    - 1882-1885 (Volume 605)
    - 1885-1891 (Volume 606)
    - 1892-1897 (Volume 607)
    - 1897-1901 (Volume 608)
    - 1904-1908 (Volume 609)
    - 1910-1914 (Volume 610)
    - 1915-1928 (Volume 611)
    - 1927-1940 (Volume 612)
  - Cash Books
    - 1880 November - 1884 May (Volume 613)
    - 1884 May - 1887 February (Volume 614A)
    - 1887 February - 1889 September (Volume 614B)
    - 1889 October - 1892 June (Volume 615)
    - 1892 June - 1895 March (Volume 616)
    - 1895 March - 1898 January (Volume 617)
    - 1898 January - 1900 October (Volume 618)
    - 1900 October - 1903 August (Volume 619)
    - 1903 Augustust - 1906 May (Volume 620)
    - 1906 May - 1910 February (Volume 621)
    - 1910 February - 1913 October (Volume 622)
    - 1913 October - 1917 May (Volume 623)
    - 1917 May - 1924 May (Volume 624)
    - 1924 May - 1934 September (Volume 625)
    - 1934 October - 1940 May (Volume 626)
- Series II: Inventories And Miscellaneous Accounts, 1881 [?] - 1931, 1947
  - General Inventory Book, 1881 [?] January - 1883 January (Volume 627)
  - Dry Goods Inventory Book, 1919 - 1931 (Volume 628)
  - Miscellaneous Inventory Book, undated (Volume 629)
  - Day Book, lumber, 1901 April - December (Volume 630)
  - Cash Book and Accounts, 1947 May - August (Volume 631)
- Series III: Invoice Books, 1888-1940
  - Invoice Books
  - 1888 (Volume 632)
  - 1890-1891 (Volume 633)
  - 1900-1901 (Volume 634)
  - 1910-1911 (Volume 635)
  - 1920-1922 (Volume 636)
  - 1930-1933 (Volume 637)
  - 1939-1940 (Volume 638 (44))